Robert Garrett Collection of Ethiopic Magic Scrolls, 1700-1900: Finding Aid C0744.04
Manuscripts Division
Robert Garrett Collection of Ethiopic Magic Scrolls
1700-1900
Manuscripts Division
Princeton University. Library. Special Collections
Garrett, Robert, b. 1875
C0744.04
4 boxes
1356 items
Consists of 162 Ethiopic magic scrolls collected by Robert Garrett (1875-1961), Princeton Class of 1897.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of 162 Ethiopic magic scrolls collected by Robert Garrett (1875-1961), Princeton Class of 1897.
Ethiopic magic scrolls are textual amulets containing brief protective and healing texts in Ge'ez and occasionally Amharic. Ethiopian Christians wore these scrolls on the body in the belief that they prevented disease, death in childbirth, demonic possession, malevolent spirits, the Evil Eye, and other sources of personal misfortune. They were generally prepared by unordained clerics (debtera), who wrote on narrow strips of parchment arranged in scroll format. The magical efficacy of these scrolls is based in large measure on a selection of amuletic texts, apotropaic prayers, charms, incantations, prayers, Scriptural quotations, miracle tales, formulas, invocations of divine names and helpful saints, and images. Most magic scrolls were activated for the use of a particular person, whose name is given. Contributing to their protective power are painted images of guardian angels with drawn swords, St. Susenyos slaying Werzelya for the protection of mothers and infants, magic squares and eight-pointed stars, the net of Solomon for capturing demons, and other figurative illustrations and designs. The magic scrolls were generally rolled up in small leather capsules, enabling them to be worn on the body. Some fairly modern magic scrolls are sewn into the capsules so that they cannot be read, but most could be opened and even hung on walls for prayer and protection. Most extant examples in the Princeton University Library date from the 18th to 20th centuries. For more information, see Jacques Mercier's Ethiopic Magic Scrolls (1979) and Art that Heals: The Image as Medicine in Ethiopia (1997).
Arrangement
Arranged by scroll number.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research use.
Custodial History
Robert Garrett acquired these magic scrolls and other Ethiopic manuscripts in the early decades of the 20th century, chiefly from Enno Littmann (1875-1958), Professor of Oriental Languages at the University of Tübingen and an eminent authority on the languages and literatures of Ethiopia and the Near East. Garrett donated his Ethiopic manuscripts and scrolls along with the bulk of his collection to the Library in 1942.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Robert Garrett in 1942.
Appraisal
No appraisal information is available.
Related Materials
Princeton University Library has two other collections of Ethiopic magic scrolls: Bruce C. Willsie Collection of Ethiopic Magic Scrolls and Princeton Collection of Ethiopic Magic Scrolls (C1296).
Garrett, Robert, b. 1875
Biographical / Historical
Robert Garrett was born in Baltimore, Maryland, on June 24, 1875. Garrett inherited his collecting interest from his father, Thomas Harrison Garrett, Princeton Class of 1868. After his father's sudden death in 1888, Garrett spent the following two and a half years traveling extensively with his mother and two brothers, Horatio and John, in Europe and the Near East. During his travels Garrett developed a particular interest in manuscripts and began collecting. He used the text Universal Paleography: or, Fac-similes of Writing of All Nations and Periods by J. B. Silvestre (tr. by Sir Frederic Madden, London, 1949-50) as his guide for collecting primary examples of every known type of script. Garrett returned to the United States in 1891 and soon after began his studies at Princeton University. He received his A.B. degree from Princeton in 1897. While in school, Garrett excelled in track and field athletics. In 1896 he competed in the first modern Olympic games in Athens, Greece, where he became the first champion in discus and shot put. After graduation he continued on in the family banking firm, Robert Garrett & Sons, in Baltimore, Maryland. However, he maintained very close contact with his alma mater and in 1905 was elected a Life Trustee of Princeton University. Throughout his career Garrett also remained dedicated to his collecting hobby. He maintained from the beginning that his collection would one day be given to the Princeton University Library so that it would always be connected with academic research. He donated the bulk of his collection to the Princeton University Library in 1942. Robert Garrett died on April 25, 1961, in Baltimore, Maryland. In the end he had amassed a collection of over 11,000 volumes of Western and non-Western manuscripts, fragments, and scrolls, originating from Europe, the Near East, Africa, Asia and Mesoamerica, ca. 1340 B.C.-1900s.
Bibliography
Ephraim Isaac, "Princeton Collection of Ethiopic Manuscripts," Princeton University Library Chronicle 42:1 (Autumn 1980), pp. 33-52. Richard Pankhurst, "Secular Themes in Ethiopian Ecclesiastical Manuscripts: V.: A Catalogue of Illustrations of Historical and Ethnographic Interest in Princeton University Library and Art Gallery," Journal of Ethiopian Studies 22 (November 1989), pp. 31-64. Don C. Skemer, "Princeton's Ethiopic Manuscript Collections at 100," Princeton University Library Chronicle 71:3 (Spring 2010), pp. 461-466.
Ethiopian magic scrolls.; Magic, Ethiopian.; Ethiopia -- History -- Sources.; Manuscripts, Ethiopic
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 1, 1850-1899; 1; Single piece of parchment (the bottom piece(s) of the scroll missing). 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a small hand (2.0-2.5mm), framed within a latticework border. 1 talismanic drawing at the top. (Box 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  The collection is open for research use.
  Scope and Contents
  Drawing: Grid of 9 squares containing alternating faces and cruciform designs. (In ink with some faded red-brown color.)
  Owner: Gäbrä Amlak (m.)
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya and Légéwon, and for the Binding of Demons, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye (Aynä T'ela) and Possession by Spirits (Nägärgar), circa 1850-1899; 1 item
    Includes the beginning of the Gospel of John.
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye (Hemamä Aynät and Aynä säbe') Prayer against the Evil Eye (Hemamä Aynät and Aynä Barya Wälégéwon), circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer Invoking "God the Most High, God the Almighty, and Mary the Mother of Our Lord" for Protection against Spells, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against Mäggañña, Shotälay, Shotälawit and Qolé, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Beginning of the Legend of Susenyos, for the Protection of Infants and Their Mothers, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 2, 1870-1899; 2; Single piece of thick parchment (the top piece(s) of the scroll missing). 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a untidy hand (4mm). 1 talismanic drawing in the middle; 1 group of talismanic "letters" (harägawi fidäl) in ink at the bottom. (Box 1)
  Drawings:
  Colored grid of 30 squares in yellow, blue, red and green.
  Group of talismanic "letters" (harägawi fidäl) in ink.
  Owner: Egzi'a Harya (f.)
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells (Mäftehé Seray), late 19th century; 1 item
    Comprises in large part magical names (asmat) and "Hebrew" letter names.
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Dissolution of Spells "of Women and Men", late 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 3, 1830-1870; 3; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a widely spaced and spidery hand (4.5-6mm), framed within a simple scalloped border. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink without color).
  Schematic eight-pointed star with central face. (In ink without color.)
  Lobed cruciform design. (In ink without color.)
  Owner: original owner's name erased and replaced by Wälättä Sellasé (f.)
  - Prayer That "Neither Evil [Things] Nor Evil Persons Might Enter the House", mid 19th century; 1 item
    Inter alia invokes the Archangel Michael.
  - Prayer for Banishing Devils, the Devil's Host, and Other Demons, Again Invoking the Archangel Michael as Well as "The 99 [Other] Archangels", mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer Spoken by "Our Lord Jesus Christ to His Disciples", mid 19th century; 1 item
    Covers inter alia salvation from sin and unspecified sickness.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 4, 1830-1870; 4; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics (now slightly faded) in an uneven hand (3-4mm), framed within a simple striated border. 3 talismanic drawings in ink with red and ochre color. Preserved within original leather cylinder pouch. (Box 1)
  Complex composition of bands and squares incorporating protective faces and schematic figures. (In ink with red color, now rubbed and faded).
  Schematic cruciform design with faces at the ends of the arms. (In ink with red and yellow color, now rubbed and faded.)
  Schematic eight-pointed star figure (?) with faces at the end of each point, and bands of protective eye motifs. (In ink with red and yellow color, now rubbed and faded.)
  Owner: Wäldä Liqanos (m.)
  - Prayer against Zar and Barya, as Well as Other Evil Spirits Many of Whom Are Designated as "The king" of Named Demons and Diseases, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Cursing Evil Spirits, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Comprises mostly secret and magical names (asmat).
  - Prayer for Expelling Evil Spirits and Releasing Individuals Possessed by Buda, Barya and Demons, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Rheumatism, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Blacksmiths, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Concluding Assertion That "These Prayers Were Written in the Blood of Jesus Christ"
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 5, 1870-1930; 5; 2 pieces of parchment sewn together (the top piece of the scroll now missing). 2 cols., written in black with rubrics, framed within a simple linear border and separated by a central colored margin (in pink, yellow and blue). 2 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Schematic eight-pointed star reduced to 9 squares with a central face motif. (In ink with black, pink, blue and yellow color).
  Cruciform design. (In ink with pink, blue and yellow color).
  Owner: original owner's named erased and replaced by Wälättä Ananya (f.)
  - Prayer for the Drowning of Demons (Mäst'emä Aganent), circa 1870-1930; 1 item
    Comprises mostly magical names (asmat).
  - Prayer for the Drowning of Demons, circa 1870-1930; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya and "All Evil Spirits", circa 1870-1930; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, Mäggañña, Qurañña and Täyazhi; Part of the Text Known as the Net of Solomon [Märbäbtä Sälomon], circa 1870-1930; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 6, 1770-1830; 6; 2 pieces of parchment sewn together (the presumed top piece is now missing – there are indications that a drawing, at least, has been cut off.) 1 col., without frame, written in black with rubrics in a reasonable and clear hand. Unusually there are no drawings (aside from the remnants of colored banding at the top.) (Box 1)
  Drawings: None.
  Owner: Wäldä Gäbre'él (m.) In two places a woman's name, Sergutä Sellasé, is included as well, and throughout a second woman's name, Wälättä Arägawi has been added later in purple ink.
  - The Text Known as the Net of Solomon; Here Simply Entitled "The Magical Names of Solomon With Which He Netted Demons as in a Fishing ", circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayer against Spells (?), Entitled S'älotä Aqweyas'at Wä'aqabyanä Seray; the Two Words Aqweyas'[at] and Aqaby[an] Are Unknown, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
  - Prayers against the Evil Eye, circa 1770-1830; 1 item
    Includes in continuo the story of the woman with an issue of blood from the Gospel of Mark.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 7, 1870-1899; 7; 2 pieces of thick parchment sewn together (the bottom of the scroll has been cut off and is missing). 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an uneven hand (5-6mm), framed within a simple linear border colored yellow. In many places missing letters from the hastily written text have been inserted above the line. 1 talismanic drawing. (Box 1)
  Drawing: Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Owner: Täklä Haymanot (m.)
  - Prayer for the Binding of "Evil Demons", late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, late 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 8, 1870-1899; 8; 4 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics (now somewhat faded) in a compact and uneven hand (3-4mm). 2 talismanic drawings and 1 chart. (Box 1)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with bright blue and faded red color).
  Grid of 24 squares each containing a separate letter of the fidäl.
  Simple motif of two crossing lobe shapes.
  Owner: Qalä Krestos (m.)
  - Prayer against Colic, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Stomach Pains, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic and Liver or Stomach Ailments, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Buda and Blacksmiths, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Barya and Légéwon, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic. A Sälam (Hymn of Salutation) to the Archangel Phanuel, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Barya, Légéwon and Inter Alia Headache, Colic, Rheumatism and Chest Pains, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, late 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 9, 1830-1870; 9; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a rather angular and untutored hand (4-5mm), framed between a fine zigzag border with traces of yellow wash. 2 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with yellow color and some decoration in red.)
  Stylized eight-pointed star motif with central face. (In ink with yellow color and some decoration in red.)
  Owner: the original owner's name, Gäbrä Egzi' (m.), has been mostly crudely crossed out in black ink, and the name of Wälättä Gäbre'él (f.) inserted between lines.
  - Prayer for the Undoing of Spells (Mäftehé Seray), mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - A Further Prayer for Undoing Spells, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 10, 1800-1850; 10; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an angular and uneven hand (2-4mm), framed between a simple linear border colored yellow. 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Schematic angel figure (wings and a face above a simple triangular design). (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Alternating bands of eye motifs and squares variously filled with stylized faces and simple cross designs. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  A protective figure with raised arms, fingers and toes unusually represented by comb-like series of lines; the figure appears to be cloaked and either side are two sets of concentric circles. The whole is set against a yellow ground and has some light red color.
  A series of bands, some with simple cross-hatching, others with eye motifs; again with red and yellow color.
  Owner: the original owner's name, Wäldä Abbeyä Egzi' (m.), which appears once, is mostly replaced by that of Wälättä Egzi' (f.)
  - Prayer for the Elimination of Evil Spirits and Demons from the House, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
    Begins with an extensive invocation comprising various magic names (asmat).
  - Prayer for Expelling Devils, Barya, Légéwon, etc, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
    in continuo
  - Prayer Known as the Net of Solomon [Märbäbtä Sälomon], circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 11, 1750-1799; 11; Edges show considerable rodent damage. 2 pieces of parchment sewn together (the top of the scroll is missing. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a very angular and square hand (3-5mm). 1 talismanic drawing. (Box 1)
  Drawing: An unusual schematic design of triangles and a central square containing a cross motif, framed within embracing "wings", the whole colored red, black and yellow.
  Owner: the original owner's name has been replaced by various others, Täsfa Maryam Männu, Wälättä Mika'él and Wälättä Wahed.
  - Prayer against Various Spells, mid/late 18th century; 1 item
    Beginning missing.
  - Prayer or Sequence of Prayers against Sorcerers, mid/late 18th century; 1 item
    In continuo. Incorporates the opening of the Gospel of John. The end of the scroll is stained and illegible.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 12, 1850-1899; 12; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an uneven hand (3-5mm). 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Roughly executed grid of squares with zigzag, dotted or block color wash infill (in red, black and faded yellow) and a central cruciform motif composed of triangles.
  A similar composition to fig. 1.
  A grid of squares with block color wash (red, black and faded yellow) or dotted infill with a stylized face motif in the center square.
  Owner: Särayä Krestos.
  - The Text Known as the Lefafä S'edq or Bandlet of Righteousness. Abbreviated Form of the Märbäbtä Sälomon or Net of Solomon, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 13, 1830-1870; 13; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together, with a thin tying strip at the top. 1 col., written in black with rubrics (now faded) in a compact and uneven hand (4-5mm), framed within a simple linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with light yellow and red color wash.
  Eight-pointed star motif with superimposed central cruciform design, a face at the center and eye motifs at the end of the four arms of the cross. (In ink with black, light red and yellow wash.
  Cruciform with two stylized human figures either side and a "shielding curtain" motif behind. The text in Amharic above the design reads, "behold a blessing; they shall not give counsel to the wise; they shall not cut for the lion."
  Owner: Gäbrä Maryam (m.)
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya and Légéwon, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against "Sickness Caused by Devils and Demons," and for the Drowning of Demons (Mäst'emä Aganent), mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Undoing of Spells (Mäftehé Seray). "Magic Names Of Spells" (Asmatä Seray), mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya and Légéwon. Another Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya and Légéwon, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 14, 1850-1899; 14; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together, with a tying strip attached at the top. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a large and uneven hand (5mm), framed with a simple linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  Guardian angel set between bands of crosses with protective eye motifs. The text reads "a picture of St. Michael." (In ink with red and yellow color.
  Another stylized guardian angel motif.
  Grid of nine squares with transverse cross motifs.
  Owner: various names appear in the invocations for protection and blessing: Wälättä Krestos (f.), Wälättä Gäbre'él (f.), Wälättä Kidan (f.), Wäldä Yohannes (m.) and Wäldä Rufa'él (m.), the latter two are repeated on the obverse.
  - Prayer against Buda, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Drowning of Demons and Devils, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against Rheumatism, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Part of the Gospel of Mark Together With Some Exegesis, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 15, 1800-1830; 15; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. The top of the scroll shows some wear and worm damage. 2 cols., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (2-3mm), separated by a decorated colored central margin with alternating transverse cruciform and lobed designs (in red and yellow). 3 particularly finely executed talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  A pair of guardian angels holding swords.
  Grid of 9 squares with overlaid crossing lobe design. The four corner squares are infilled with a checkerboard design and the central square contains a face motif; beneath is a finely drawn band of haräg or vine motif.
  Another grid of 9 squares overlying a stylized eight-pointed star or eight-armed cruciform design with birds' heads in the four corner squares, and a transverse cross of protective eye motifs in the center.
  Owner: the original owner's name appears to have been ...lä Giyorgis (m.), but this has been erased and replaced throughout by Haylä Ab.
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Légéwon, early 19th century; 1 item
  - Set of Prayers against Barya and Légéwon, early 19th century; 1 item
  - Solomon's Prayer for Drowning Demons (Mäst'emä Sälomon Zä'ast'ämon Lä'aganent, early 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Rheumatism, early 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Rheumatism, early 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against "Foul Légéwon Who Cuts the Hearts of Men", early 19th century; 1 item
  - The Prayer of Susenyos "For Keeping Sickness from Suckling Infants And for Women Whose Children Do Not Survive", early 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Tempests (?) [awlo], early 19th century; 1 item
    Text partly erased and difficult to read.
  - Prayer against Liver or Stomach Disease and Colic. Sälam (Hymn Of Salutation) to the Archangel Phanuel, early 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 16, 1830-1870; 16; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a moderate hand (4-5mm), framed within a linear border showing traces of yellow color. 1 talismanic drawing, and one ornamental band. (Box 1)
  Three crosses, the center one decorated. ornamental band.
  Owner: the name Wälättä Mika'él appears as a later addition.
  - The Text Known as the Lefafä S'edq or Bandlet of Righteousness; Prayer of the Agony of Death (S'a'rä Mot), mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer of the Road to Heaven (Mängädä Sämay), mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 17, 1850-1899; 17; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a very uneven and untutored hand (7-8mm). 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 1)
  A complex series of decorated bands incorporating squares with infill of transverse crosses and lobes and, in the upper portion, a central face motif. (In ink with red-brown and yellow color.)
  A similar composition to 1, but with a stylized equine figure at the top bearing a face and, lower down, another face motif at the centre of 9 squares.
  A third elongated drawing of similar format, but with 4 stylized human figures at top above a grid of 20 squares variously infilled with black, red-brown and yellow color.
  Owner: two names occur, Gäbr[ä] Musé and Gäbr[ä] Qal, both m.
  - Prayer against Terror by Day or Night Together With a Sälam (Hymn Of Salutation) to Phanuel, the Expeller of Demons, and the Hymn Särawitä Mäla'ektihu or the Host of His Angels, circa 1850-1899; 1 item
  - Prayer against "all Evil Demons, Spells of Sorcerers, Buda, Barya, Headache, Colic, Rheumatism and All Types of Disease", circa 1850-1899; 1 item
    In continuo from the preceding text